Guide to the Roberta Yerkes Blanshard Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Roberta Yerkes Blanshard papers
1914-2006
1959-1997
MS 1566
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.52
(4 boxes)
The papers consist of subject files, containing correspondence and memorabilia, of Roberta Yerkes Blanshard. The majority of the files relate to the Yale University Press and include a reminiscence of her years with the press. Correspondents in these files include authors with whom she worked, Yale Press staff members, and printers and typographers who worked for the press. There are also files on her friend, Ada Louise Comstock Notestein.
Blanshard, Roberta Yerkes, 1907-2001
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Roberta Yerkes Blanshard, 1998; transferred from Yale University Press, 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Brand Blanshard Papers (MS 1488). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.Robert Mearns Yerkes Papers (MS 569). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Biographical / Historical
Roberta Yerkes Blanshard was born in 1907, the daughter of Robert Mearns and Ada Watterson Yerkes. She attended Bryn Mawr College and joined the Yale University Press staff following graduation in 1929. She remained in the editorial department of the press until 1959. In 1969, she married Brand Blanshard, a Yale professor of philosophy. Blanshard died in Hamden, Connecticut in 2001.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of subject files, containing correspondence and memorabilia, of Roberta Yerkes Blanshard. The majority of the files relate to the Yale University Press and include a reminiscence of her years with the press. Correspondents in these files include authors with whom she worked, Yale Press staff members, and printers and typographers who worked for the press. There are also files on her friend, Ada Louise Comstock Notestein.
Publishers and publishing; Blanshard, Roberta Yerkes, 1907-2001; Yale University Press
- Inventory
  - Bolton, Francis, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notestein, Ada Louise Comstock
    - Biographical, Circa 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Clemedtson, Susan, 1971-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cronkhite, Bernice Brown, 1975-1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - House
      General
      See: Inventory Folder 6
    - Lecture at Comstock House in Moorhead, Minnesota, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Loeffler, Robert, 1975-1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Obituaries, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Schlesinger Library, 1973-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Smith College, 1949-1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Solomon, Barbara, 1973-1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Williams, Anne, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - O'Meara, Eva
    - Biographical, 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Smith, Joel Sumner [article and notes], 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Yale University Press
    - "Memories of the Yale University Press"
      - Manuscript, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Reference material and notes
        - Catalogues, 1938, 1947, 1958, 1960, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        - Clippings, 1944, 1953-1991 (Box 1, Folder 16)
        - Corwin, Margaret, [includes photograph], 1914, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 17)
        - Davidson, Eugene A., 1956, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 18)
        - Davis, Malcolm, Circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 19)
        - Day, Wilhelmina Johnson, 1948, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 20)
        - Donaldson, Norman V., 1952-1964 (Box 2, Folder 21)
        - Goodman, Olive, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 22)
        - Histories, 1920, 1958, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 23)
        - Hocking, William Ernest, 1951-1959 (Box 2, Folder 24)
        - Homes, 1956-1993 (Box 2, Folder 25)
        - Horne, David and Elinor, 1958-1995 (Box 2, Folder 26)
        - Kerr, Chester, 1968, 1983, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 27)
        - Moseley, Laura Hadley, 1979, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 28)
        - Resignation, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 29)
        - Souvenirs, 1941-1983 (Box 2, Folder 30)
        - Staff, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 31)
        - Wright, Mabel K., 1964, 1980, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Typographers and printers
    - Eisenman, Alvin, 1958, 1979, 1991, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Hoover, Roland A., 1984, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - McCrillis, John, 1983-1997 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Rollins, Carl, 1932-1993 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Rueckert, Karl, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Vilas, Charles and Margaret, 1963, 1987-1993 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Wayzgoose, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence with authors
    - Appreciations, 1955-1959 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Griffin, Donald, 1987-1994 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Kinsey, Joseph Howard, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - O'Neill, Carlotta, 1956-1958, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Tolstoy, Alexandra Lvovna, 1975-1981 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence with staff members
    - Carroll, Jane and Mark, 1957-1996 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Cuningham, Charles E., 1987 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Palmer, Barbara, 1982-1997 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Underwood, Richard, 1958-1987 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Weld, Ellen, 1985-1994 (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Additional material, 1988-2006; Accession 2013-M-069
  Scope and Contents
  The majority of the correspondence consists of letters exchanged by Ann Baer and Roberta Blanshard, 1988-2000. There is also a small amount of Ann Baer's orrespondence with Roland Hoover, Jane Olson, Tina Wheeler, and the Yale University Press. The Press letters discuss her donation of the material and include an explanation of the start of the correspondence.
  - Correspondence, 1988-2006 (Box 1)